Henry Shapiro Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- United Press International, Moscow Bureau, 1920-1973 (Box 4-133)
  - Reference File, 1920-1973 (Box 6-25)
    - Unidentified
      - Clippings, 1931-1973, undated, (7 folders); (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - Russian documents, undated
      - Russian printed matter, 1959-1973, undated
  - Wire Service Reports, 1931-1971 (Box 26-133)
    Copies of cables and telegrams.
    Organized by month and year as filed by Shapiro.
    - Incoming messages (Box 26)
      - 1946, Nov.
      - circa 1946, Jan.-circa 1948, Dec., (4 folders)
      - 1947
        - Jan.-May, (6 folders)
        - June-Sept., (3 folders) (Box 27)
      - 1948, Jan.-Apr., (3 folders)
    - Outgoing
      - 1931, Jan.-Dec., (9 folders)
      - circa 1931, Jan.-circa 1933, Dec., (12 folders) (Box 28)
      - 1932, Jan.-1933, Oct., (17 folders) (Box 29)
      - 1935, Dec.-1938, Dec., (14 folders) (Box 30)
      - 1939
        - Jan.-Mar., (3 folders)
        - Apr.-Dec., (12 folders) (Box 31)
      - 1940, Jan.-1941, Aug., (10 folders) (Box 32)
      - circa 1941, (2 folders)
      - circa 1946, Jan.-circa 1948, Dec., (12 folders) (Box 33)
      - 1946, Oct.-Dec., (12 folders) (Box 34)
      - 1947 (Box 35)
        - Jan.-Feb., (5 folders)
        - Mar.-Apr., (8 folders); (12 folders) (Box 36, Box 37)
        - May, (3 folders)
        - June-Nov., (12 folders) (Box 38)
        - Dec., (4 folders) (Box 39)
      - 1948
        - Jan.-Mar., (8 folders)
        - Apr.-July, (9 folders) (Box 40)
        - Aug., (3 folders) (Box 41)
        - Sept.-Nov., (8 folders)
        - Dec., (2 folders) (Box 42)
      - 1949
        - Jan.-Feb., (7 folders)
        - Mar.-May, (14 folders) (Box 43)
        - June-Sept., (13 folders) (Box 44)
        - Oct.-Dec., (11 folders) (Box 45)
      - 1950, Jan.-Mar., (12 folders) (Box 46)
      - 1952 (Box 47)
        - Feb.-Aug., (14 folders)
        - Sept.-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 48)
      - 1953, Nov.
      - 1954
        - Jan.-Mar., (4 folders)
        - Apr.-Dec., (9 folders) (Box 49)
      - 1955
        - Jan.-Sept., (7 folders)
        - Oct.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 50)
      - 1956, Aug., (4 folders)
      - 1957
        - May, (2 folders)
        - June-Oct., (10 folders) (Box 51)
      - 1961 (Box 52)
        - Aug., Nov., (12 folders)
        - Dec., (5 folders) (Box 53)
      - 1962
        - May-June, (6 folders)
        - July-Aug., (14 folders) (Box 54)
        - Sept., (8 folders) (Box 55)
      - 1963
        - Jan., (6 folders)
        - Feb.-Apr., (12 folders) (Box 56)
        - May-June, (11 folders) (Box 57)
        - July, (14 folders) (Box 58)
        - Aug., Oct., (12 folders) (Box 59)
        - Nov., (12 folders) (Box 60)
        - Dec., (15 folders) (Box 61)
      - 1964 (Box 62)
        - Jan., (11 folders)
        - Feb., (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box 63)
        - Mar., (11 folders)
        - Apr., June-July, (16 folders) (Box 64)
        - Aug., (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 65)
      - 1965
        - Jan., (13 folders); (4 folders) (Box 66)
        - Feb., (11 folders); (9 folders) (Box 67)
        - Mar., (7 folders); (12 folders) (Box 68)
        - Apr., (2 folders); (14 folders) (Box 69)
        - May, (16 folders) (Box 70)
        - June, (10 folders) (Box 71)
        - July, (3 folders); (12 folders) (Box 72)
        - Aug., (3 folders); (8 folders) (Box 73)
        - Dec., (5 folders)
      - 1966 (Box 74)
        - Jan., (15 folders)
        - Feb., (12 folders) (Box 75)
        - Mar., (12 folders) (Box 76)
        - Apr.-June, (13 folders) (Box 77)
        - July, (11 folders); (4 folders) (Box 78, Box 79)
        - Aug., (8 folders); (10 folders) (Box 80)
        - Sept., (8 folders); (12 folders) (Box 81)
        - Oct., (4 folders); (16 folders) (Box 82)
        - Nov., (13 folders); (5 folders) (Box 83, Box 84)
        - Dec., (7 folders); (15 folders) (Box 85)
      - 1967 (Box 86)
        - Jan., (13 folders); (7 folders) (Box 87)
        - Feb., (7 folders); (10 folders) (Box 88)
        - Mar., (5 folders); (15 folders); (2 folders) (Box 89, Box 90)
        - Apr., (13 folders); (8 folders) (Box 91)
        - May, (6 folders); (14 folders); (2 folders) (Box 92, Box 93)
        - June, (13 folders) (Box 94)
        - July, (12 folders); (6 folders) (Box 95, Box 96)
        - Aug., (11 folders)
        - Sept., (14 folders); (3 folders) (Box 97, Box 98)
        - Oct., (10 folders); (9 folders) (Box 99)
        - Nov., (5 folders) (Box 100)
        - Dec., (9 folders); (3 folders) (Box 101)
      - 1968
        - Jan., (9 folders); (4 folders) (Box 102)
        - Feb., (8 folders)
        - Mar., (10 folders) (Box 103)
        - Apr., (12 folders) (Box 104)
        - May, (10 folders) (Box 105)
        - June, (12 folders) (Box 106)
        - July, (10 folders); (5 folders) (Box 107, Box 108)
        - Aug., (6 folders); (8 folders) (Box 109)
        - Sept., (3 folders); (7 folders) (Box 110)
        - Oct., (5 folders) (Box 111)
        - Nov., (5 folders); (4 folders) (Box 112)
        - Dec., (7 folders)
      - 1969 (Box 113)
        - Jan., (11 folders)
        - Feb., (7 folders) (Box 114)
        - Mar., (3 folders); (4 folders) (Box 115)
        - Apr., (7 folders)
        - May-June, (12 folders) (Box 116)
        - July, (7 folders) (Box 117)
        - Aug., (3 folders) (Box 118)
        - Sept., (6 folders)
        - Oct., (4 folders); (5 folders) (Box 119)
        - Nov., (6 folders)
        - Dec., (6 folders) (Box 120)
      - 1970
        - Jan., (6 folders)
        - Feb.-Mar., (12 folders) (Box 121)
        - Apr., (9 folders) (Box 122)
        - May, (6 folders) (Box 123)
        - June, (4 folders) (Box 124)
        - July, (8 folders)
        - Aug.-Sept., (12 folders) (Box 125)
        - Oct., (8 folders) (Box 126)
        - Nov., (2 folders); (3 folders) (Box 127)
        - Dec., (6 folders)
      - 1971
        - Jan., (3 folders) (Box 128)
        - Feb.-Mar., (10 folders)
        - Apr.-May, (13 folders) (Box 129)
        - June-July, (11 folders) (Box 130)
        - Aug.-Oct., (11 folders) (Box 131)
      - Undated, (9 folders) (Box 132, Box 133)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1937-1987 (Box 134-138)
  Articles, book, interviews, lectures, memoir, and notes.
  - Articles (Box 134)
    - Drafts, 1947-1985, undated, (14 folders)
    - Printed, 1947-1987, undated, (9 folders) (Box 135)
  - Book, L'U.R.S.S. après Staline
    - Drafts, 1954, (3 folders)
    - Posters, undated
    - Serializations, 1954 See also Oversize, (5 folders)
  - Fragments, 1974, undated, (2 folders) (Box 136)
  - Interviews, 1957-1978, undated, (3 folders)
  - Lectures
    - Clippings, 1946-1977, undated
    - Engagements
      - Creighton University, Omaha, Nebr., 1983
      - Milwaukee Journal, Milwaukee, Wis., 1974
      - University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, 1980-1984
      - University of Miami, Miami, Fla., 1975
      - University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis., 1965-1978, (2 folders)
    - Programs and announcements, 1944-1983, undated, (2 folders)
    - Questions, 1944 (Box 137)
    - Notes, 1974-1985, undated, (3 folders)
  - Memoir, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
  - Notes (Box 138)
    - Détente, undated
    - Economy, undated
    - Ideology, undated See also Container 15, same heading
    - Miscellaneous, undated, (2 folders)
    - Politics, undated
    - Various countries, undated
  - Writings by others, 1937-1973, undated, (2 folders)
  - Unidentified, 1958-1972, undated, (2 folders)
- Additions, 1931-1990 (Box 139-148)
  Two additions containing correspondence, notebooks, reference files, speeches and writings, wire service reports, photographs, personal file, and miscellany.
  Arranged by addition and alphabetically by type of material or topic therein.
  - Addition I (Box 139)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1990, undated, (16 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1943-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 140)
    - Nieman Foundation for Journalism, 1948, 1954, undated
    - Personal file, 1953-1983, undated
    - Photographs and drawing, 1963-1979, undated
    - Reference file (Box 141)
      - Art, literature, and theater, 1953, undated
      - Beriia, L. P., 1953, undated
      - Bulganin, Nikolay A.
        - Clippings, 1955-1958, undated
        - Miscellany, 1955-1963, (3 folders)
      - China, 1962-1963, (3 folders)
      - Civil rights, 1936-1953, undated
      - Education
        - Clippings, 1954-1967, undated
        - Miscellany, 1954-1967, undated, (2 folders)
      - Espionage, 1965-1969, undated
      - Germany
        - Berlin conference, 1945
        - Defeat, 1945
      - Great Britain, visit of Nikita Khrushchev and Nikolay A. Bulganin, 1956
      - International incidents (Box 142)
      - Industry, 1956-1966
        - Clippings, 1954-1967
        - Miscellany, 1959-1969, undated
      - Jews, 1937-1939, undated
      - Kosygin, Aleksey N., 1955-1968, undated, (2 folders)
      - Maritime commerce, 1961-1969, undated
      - Miscellany
        - Articles and reports, 1938-1954, 1972, undated, (3 folders)
        - Clippings, 1945-1979, undated
        - Wire service reports, 1933-1969, undated, (2 folders)
      - Molotov, Vyacheslav M.
        - Clippings, 1955-1968, undated
        - Miscellany, 1954-1969, undated
      - Poland, 1945, undated
      - Stalin, Joseph (Box 143)
        - Clippings, 1931-1961, undated, (6 folders)
        - Miscellany, 1948, 1955-1970, undated, (2 folders)
      - Zhukov, Georgii K., 1955-1956, 1969
    - Speeches and writings file (Box 144)
      - Articles
        - Drafts, 1955-1984, undated, (6 folders)
        - Printed, 1942-1984, undated, (2 folders)
      - Books
        - Memoirs, correspondence and notes, 1942-1973, undated
        - Miscellany, 1948-1963, undated
        - Project with Arthur Goodfriend, drafts, undated, (3 folders)
        - L'U.R.S.S. après Staline, drafts, 1954, (4 folders) (Box 145)
      - Interviews
        - By Shapiro, 1957-1972, undated, (2 folders)
        - With Shapiro, 1946-1984, undated, (2 folders)
      - Lectures, arrangements and clippings
        - 1944-1966, (3 folders)
        - 1970-1985, undated, (9 folders) (Box 146)
      - Letter to the editor, 1979
      - Notes, undated, (3 folders)
      - Reviews, 1947, undated
      - Unidentified and fragmentary
        - 1985-1986, undated
        - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 147)
    - Television contract negotiations with USSR, 1961-1969, undated, (3 folders)
  - Wire service reports
    - 1947, 1963-1972, undated, (9 folders)
    - Undated, (11 folders) (Box 148)
  - Addition II (Box 149)
    - Speeches and writings file
      - Notebooks
        - 1941-1948
        - circa 1960-circa 1969, (2 folders)
        - circa 1970-circa 1979, (1 folder) (Box 150)
        - Undated, (1 folder) (Box 151)
- Oversize, 1954 (Box OV 1)
  Newspaper serializations of Shapiro's book, L'U.R.S.S. après Staline.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Speeches and Writings File (Box OV 1)
    - Book, L'U.R.S.S. après Staline
      - Serializations, 1954 (Container 135)